CYCLOPS

Fritz Leiber

As the Flea fell out of Moon’s shadow into sunlight, its frame and skin began to squeak and ping from the sudden heat, like an old aluminum house at dawn. To the three crewmen of the Flea it was a welcome relief to the silence of free fall, although only five minutes had passed since brennschluss. This was starting out to be an eerie jump. The stars through the big curved spacescreen looked like spiders’ eyes in a vast black nest.

Of course Pyne or Allison or Ness might have spoken or hummed or even jingled in a close-cupped hand some coins or lunar curio-nuggets. But there are times in space when such deliberate sounds only intensify the silence, like whispering in a haunted house. Everywhere you see double stars like eyes and you almost think that the spiders are at last going to spring.

The sun’s fierce ion-lashing rays, striking Flea from behind, didn’t make the tiniest highlight, only some faintly milky patches where the screen was dust-peppered. It may have been only these false nebulas which determined the remarks Ness ventured, now that the ship herself had cleared her throat with her pongings and creakings, like some crusty four-star captain indicating speech was permitted. Ness himself wasn’t clear as to what had touched off his thoughts.

“I wonder if there was Life before Life” he said. “I mean in the soup of a stellar-planetary system forming from the original whirlpool. There’d be all the needful elements in the dust, I’d think. And then suppose the heat of an older star—a close double—or of a premature atomic flickering in the central mass struck out and bred those elements. That could have happened here, you know. Pluto may be the cinder of a white dwarf.”

Allison shook his head, though his gaze shifted toward the great nebula beside Orion’s sword. “You’d never get the right ecospheric conditions,” he answered drily “or adequate concentrations of matter.”

“But suppose you did,” Pyne granted in his large easy voice. “What then, Ness? What are you driving at?”

“Well, it would be a different life from ours,” Ness replied haltingly, wondering himself what he was driving at and why. “Born more than halfway between Earth and space, you might say. In a tenuous space marsh. Not planet-bound. A primal life. The Old Life, if we’re the New. A different life with different powers.”

“The old Is-There-Life-in-the-Vacuum-of-Space buzz?” Pyne chuckled loudly but unmockingly. “They haven’t found any in the crevices of the moon, even now when we’re digging ‘em deep. Any, that is, we mightn’t have brought ourselves.”

“Ostwald thought that life came to Earth from outside, didn’t he?” Ness asked. “Some of the old boys made smart guesses.”

“He was thinking of bacterial spores driven by light pressure,” Allison explained. “Nobody believes that any more.” He paused. “Of course there is viral life in the stratosphere of Venus.”

“I was thinking of something bigger,” Ness said.

“A space squid with a tungsten gut and a sweet tooth for monatomic hydrogen? A living spaceship from a phylum Linnaeus knew only in nightmares?” Pyne laughed. “You were a kid in the Yukon, Ness. Some winter mornings you wouldn’t see smoke coming from the cabin on the next ridge but one, and you’d wonder if your neighbors and their little girl had been eaten by wolves. Now the Outward Bound misses her wireless contact with Moon Central and we’re routined to check up and get the same feeling. You’re a sensitive guy, Ness. And come to think of it, I’m thinking of something in your records.”

“Irregular ESP,” Ness said distastefully. “The psychers saw some coincidences where I didn’t. It’s a great gag.” His lips shut firmly.

“Oh, sure,” Pyne agreed carelessly. He looked at Ness a moment longer, then frowned at the stars.

The ship was utterly quiet again, its temperature change complete. A few motes of dust danced in the sunlit nose around the three unoccupied seats. The two small goldfish revolved in their bubbly greenish globe bracketed to the ship’s back where the men tried to relax, floating uneasily. The atmosphere of a long-deserted church had returned. The stars in their twos and fours in Taurus dead ahead still looked like spiders’ eyes.

Ness thought, Pyne’s right, of course. He knows my background. The imagination of the lonely. Idiot psychers, to make me doubt even my thoughts are mine. Idiot pseudosensitivity. I shouldn’t find anything eerie in this jump from a dead world to an unborn ship circling it. The Outward Bound, our first starship is being built in orbit around the moon simply because, now that the lunar mines and smelters and rolling mills are working, it’s a lot cheaper to lift material from Luna than from Earth. Not to create shiver effects. This is the fifth time Outward Bound missed her wireless contact. Three times it turned out to be nothing but a tongue of the solar storm licking out between the starship and Luna. And once, their oversight—big laugh. Every time we checked the construction team was as snug in their living globe as bugs in a blanket. We’ve been afraid of a secret strike by the Russians or the Congo, but that’s moonshine.

The false nebulas and dust motes vanished. The Flea had fallen out of the sunlight into Earth’s shadow. She began to clear her throat in reverse. Once again the simple stimulus pulled aside a curtain in Ness’ mind.

“I like your vacuum octopuses, Pyne,” he mused. “I even think living beings born in young stardust could travel across interstellar space. Existing in weak gravity or none at all, they’d live longer, like sea creatures. They’d have tissues to resist airlessness and cold. Deep-sea creatures are built to oppose positive pressure; they’d be built to oppose negative. Their mouths and other orifices would be double, like airlocks. And once launched on their courses in the light-webbed intersteller dark, they’d hibernate or go into complete deep-freeze. A thousand years, a million, what would it matter? Time would stop for them until they were warmed by their target star.”

Allison stared at him. “You’re seriously suggesting an animal with the velocity of a rocket?”

Ness thought, Somebody is. He said, “They’d be a sort of squid. Pyne’s idea. Maybe like a ramjet they’d gather and eject the dust they drive through. Maybe communities of them would help one member gather speed, like step rockets.”

“Like bloody acrobats,” Pyne muttered. “Squid pyramids.”

“Living speeding cones breaking away at the bottom,” Ness agreed. “But they wouldn’t need tremendous velocities. They’d have time. They’d go in Hohman-type minimum-energy orbits from star to star. They’d take off in the general direction their own stellar system was moving and slowly catch up with another star moving in the same general direction. For instance, any being—or any slow starship or traveling planet, for that matter—would always be coming toward our sun from Lepus, or thereabouts.”

“That piddling constellation under Orion’s feet? Why from there?” Pyne demanded.

“Because that’s at the opposite end of the starfields from Hercules, the constellation toward which Sol moves at about 12 miles a second. Anything slow catching up with Sol would come from Lepus. If it were going 30 miles a second—stars average about 20—and if it caught up with Earth when Earth was starting to swing ahead of the sun, then Earth’s 18 miles a second and Sol’s 12 would add up to the newcomer’s 30. It could go into orbit around Earth or Moon with no braking at all.”

“But traveling at 30 miles per second, interstellar trips would take what they call forever,” Pyne objected.

Ness shook his head. “Only 25,000 years to Alpha Centaurus and a million and a third to the Pleiades. Time spans like that are trifles to the creatures I have in mind.”

“Double or triple those estimates for overtaking time,” Pyne insisted.

Allison snorted, “Some creatures! Well, since anything goes in this bull session, I suppose they’d know what course to take between the stars by magic.”

“No magic,” Ness answered softly. “Creatures with such life spans, adding memory to memory, would see the stars moving, like that goldfish watching the slow swing of crumbs in his globe. Their eye would be like a great wide-angle astronomical telescope. They’d center it on their target star, allowing for its drift, and sleep their way to it, frozen like death.”

“With no course corrections for a million years?” Pyne’s voice was simply curious.

Ness frowned, his eyes narrowing sleepily. “Maybe a little of their eye would stay alive, warmed by the focused sunlight. The retina and a few tracks in the nervous system. Three of their squid-like jets—”

“What would motivate such creatures?” Allison asked.

“Curiosity, adventure, desire for warmth if their proto- flickered out,” Ness replied, then added softly, “hunger.”

The pilot’s board buzzed.

“Outward Bound’s only a half hour away,” Pyne said. “We’ll suit up now and you two will arm the ship. Space-to-space rockets, jet grenades directed outward and set to fire from the board—the works.”

Allison said, “You don’t believe—” and stopped.

“I believe in danger,” Pyne said, “and maybe just a little in Ness’ psychers.”

“I don’t,” Ness protested.

“Then you shouldn’t have told us your dreams,” Pyne said. His mouth laughed, but his eyes didn’t, as, reaching for his suit, he glanced out at the arachnid-eyed stars.

One short deceleration burst, a longer one, a tiny correction nudge, and the Flea hung beside the Outward Bound. The three men sat side by side now, strapped in the nose. Pyne in the pilot’s seat, Allison to his left with the firing board for the new-mounted artillery, Ness to Pyne’s right with the hot mike to Moon Central.

In decelerating, the Flea had come around so that they faced the moon again. It hung in the right end of the screen, its cratered bulk near full phase. In the other end was the dark globe or the construction team’s quarters, rotating very slowly, its portholes ominously black. Between these spheres, one inky, one more than half alight, there stretched against the starfields the vast long empty skeleton of the starship, three-quarters sheathed.

But no space-suited figures crawled on it anywhere, nor any of the eight-armed manipulation vehicles called spiders. Several skin sections drifted loose, reflecting moonlight.

The effect was dismal, as of a building project abandoned for millennia, not one that had been busy with workers and that had talked to Moon Central only a quarter day ago.

Then into the right end of the spacescreen there came gently bobbing, pressed to the transparency of the screen, a human skull. All three men saw it at once and for the moment could only stare at the ivory-hued jawless irregular sphere with its great black orbits and triangular nasal opening.

The sharpest horror of the thing lay in its movements. Either the Flea had stopped so very close to it that it had been attracted at once by the moonship’s miniscule gravity, or else it had been traveling very slowly toward the moonship. But in either case it must also have been rotating slowly, to account for the way it now rocked back and forth against the spacescreen, the cheekbones stopping and reversing each roll, as if it were slowly shaking its head or else peering into the cabin first with one eye, then the other, through each of which, from time to time, a star glittered. This made them notice the great holes blasted or eaten from the skull’s top and back. A few inches behind it drifted a human femur.

Ness thought, it’s nuzzling the screen. No, it’s librating like the moon. Why should a skull look so much more essentially human and feelingful than a face? Our common denominator? Rock mated to life. Intelligence shaped in stone. The earliest of all sculptures. Craggy mountains… and the moon.

Allison thought, this is quite impossible—unless the construction team’s doctor kept a skeleton. Dead flesh doesn’t vanish in space, whether the man dies by accident, sickness, or a blaster. The place for bones is Earth, where there are beasts and birds to rip the flesh away, and maggots and beetles to tidy up, and microbes and water to leach out the last taint of color. Space is where everything lasts, safe from oxygen, acids, everything but the tiny hammers of radiation and the lone wandering ions and dust grains. Yet this skull isn’t even faintly pink. It’s been sucked dry.

Pyne thought, it’s a danger sign and forgot it. He scanned swiftly, searchingly.

There could be any number of hiders inside the partially sheathed starship, but he saw none. He saw bones, then another skull, tiny as a tooth in the distance. It was beginning to look as if there weren’t a survivor.

Then something changed in the edge of his vision and he swung to the left.

The dark construction sphere, in rotating, had become deformed. The side swinging into view was crushed inward as if by some unimaginably great judo chop. An opening yards long, feet high, had been torn in the globe’s equator. Only darkness inside—

No. Now moonlight began to show something long and straight and pale and divided into sections like a white tape-measure stretched out straight, only longer and much wider. The pale band widened and narrowed rhythmically.

And now, just above the band’s center, behind it in the darkness of the smashed globe, a pale dark-centered circle big as a man’s chest appeared. It brightened in the moonlight, brightened, and then when that eye—for Pyne was sure suddenly it was a single great eye—when that eye became its brightest, gazing directly at Flea, it began to move toward him, slowly at first, then very swiftly, and the white band came with it. As the whole launched out of the construction globe, he saw that it was a round flat object about eight yards in diameter and a yard in thickness, with single eye and great white toothwall in front and with a dozen jets behind.

Pyne would never have noted its circularity except that his fingers had automatically fired Flea’s jets to take the little ship upward out of the path of the crushing stroke. Now the creature’s dull gray flesh was passing under the Flea—straight into its fiery jets—when two gray striated tentacles whipped upward from beside the great eye, like steel cables snapped under tension. They struck the Flea ringingly, grooving its double skin where they clutched, whitening the spacescreen where one gripped.

A strong vibration went through the ship, the suits, the men. Then the Flea was flipped over, so that all three of them were staring straight down at the creature.

At that instant Allison called, “Mask!” and fired all the forward rockets. Their explosion a scant ten yards away battered the Flea—explosion front almost as harsh as shock wave—and almost blinded the three men despite the polarization “Mask” of their face plates. Yet the explosions didn’t snap or shake loose the tentacles, and when the men saw again, there was the creature with four holes gaping in it, each a yard across, and all still bathed by the fiery tongues of the Flea’s jets.

Then the creature drew itself up through the yellow flames and enfolded the Flea.

Allison fired the dozen jet grenades unlaunched; recoiling pressures raised inward blisters which broke to let in brief fires. Then the Flea was swinging and spinning, its sides buckling. Allison fired what was left, Pyne turned the jets to full power—and suddenly the convulsions were over.

What still clung against the spacescreen was the forward rags of the creature, its tatters of skin thick as armor plate, its inner vessels like heavy piping, and among them still a few bones. There were the stumps of the gripping tentacles and the great white mouth below them—a mouth which they saw now was double, with one toothplate in front and one behind. The forward set were still shutting and opening feebly, grating against the spacescreen. It made Ness think of the rocking of the skull.

And there was the eye. Its cornea and lens had been blasted away, baring the black retina. On this were permanent white markings in a pattern all of them slowly recognized: the constellation Hercules and around it Draco and Corona Borealis and a part of Ophiuchus and Lyra with great Vega. In the center was a white round bigger than all the rest—a star that didn’t fit, unless it were Sol as seen from the orbit of Saturn. That, Pyne decided, was where the creature had awakened. The white markings would be a sort of scar tissue—the markings of light focused there for eons. Most of the lightscars were not dots but lines recording the movements of the stars over about the last quarter million years.

He said grudgingly, “That’s your alien, all right, Ness.”

Ness nodded. “One of them,” he said softly.